A Guide to the Gaines Family Papers, 1810-1905
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Gaines Family Papers 1810-1905
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3596
This collection consists of 1700 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection is deposit of Mr. Richard V. Gaines of Do Well, Virginia, November 8, 1950.
Scope and Content Information
The Gaines family papers, principally those of Richard V. and Richard H., consist of roughly 1700 items, 1810-1928, dealing primarily with the activities of that family of Charlotte County. Among the business papers there are materials on the Virginia grange (Patrons of Husbandry) and some information on farming and education in Virginia and New York State. The bills and receipts range from 1840 to 1902. There are a number of hand copied music manuscripts of Italian, French and German composers, miscellaneous classroom notes and a folio of one hundred portraits of famous individuals. The miscellaneous series also contains genealogy of the Gaines family, and speeches regarding the 1860 election and secession.
Of interest is a ledger containing ages of slaves, pedigrees of horses, etc., 1810-1827.
Organization
There was no basic organization to the unsorted collection and has therefore been arranged into Personal and business correspondence, Business papers, Miscellaneous notebooks, song books, and ledgers, and finally a Miscellaneous group. Due to the small size of the collection it was not arranged into series but is merely listed as to box contents.
Contents List
- Personal Correspondence 1848-1887, 600 items. (Box 1)
- Personal Correspondence 1888-1900, 600 items. (Box 2)
- Personal Correspondence 1900-1935, undated (Box 3)
- Personal Correspondence 1835-1885 (Box 3)
- Business Correspondence 1886-1902, undated (Box 4)
- Expense Books 1865-1873 (Box 4)
- Clarinet music n.d. (Box 4)
- Greek notes 1814 (?) (Box 4)
- Hand copied music notes n.d.
- Genealogy notes October-March, 1882-1823 (Box 4)
- Century Gallery of One Hundred Portraits ca. 1897 (Box 5)
- Hand copied music book of Italian, French and German compositions n.d. (Box 5)
- Speeches on temperance and Southern schools n.d. (Box 5)
- Genealogy of Gaines family n.d. (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous envelopes n.d. (Box 5)
- In Memorium(Broadside for Richard Gaines) 1886 (Box 5)
- Printed speeches on 1860 elections, Democratic Conventions, etc. ca. 1860 (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 5)
- Bills and receipts 1840-1860, 600 items. (Box 6)
- Business materials
- Bills and receipts 1861-1902, n.d. (Box 7)
- Contracts, insurance policies 1850-1870, 15 items. (Box 7)
- Cancelled checks 1870-1901, 800 items. (Box 7)